<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter xml:id="chap9"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Equations and Graphs</title>
    <introduction>

        <sidebyside width="60%" margins="0% 40%"><image source="images/shutterstock_67170118.jpg"><description>squirrel</description></image></sidebyside>
        <sidebyside width="60%" margins="0% 40%"><image source="images/squirrel.jpg"><description>squirrel</description></image></sidebyside>

    <p>
        <term>Linear programming</term><idx>linear programming</idx> is an application of linear systems developed in the 1940s to solve complex optimization problems during wartime operations. Today linear programming is used for scheduling and allocation of resources, in shipping and telecommunications networks, and in the selection of stocks and bonds for portfolios. In 1980, the computer scientist Laszlo Lovasz said that "If one would take statistics about which  mathematical problem is using up most of the computer time in the world, ... the answer would probably be linear programming."
    </p>
    <p>
        George Dantzig (1914-2005) invented the simplex method for solving linear programming problems in 1947. His first application of the method was to determine an adequate diet of least cost. This problem involved nine equations in 77 unknowns, and took 120 days to solve using the desk calculators available at the time. In this chapter we use a graphing technique to solve problems in two unknowns. For example, the diet of the Columbian ground squirrel consists of two foods: grass and forb, a type of flowering weed. Small animals spend most of their time foraging for food, but must also be alert for predators. Which foraging strategy favors survival: should the squirrel try to satisfy its dietary requirements in minimum time, thus minimizing its exposure to predators and the elements, or should it try to maximize its intake of nutrients?
    </p>
    <p>
        Using linear programming, Gary Belovsky of Notre Dame University identified the optimal amounts of forb and grass for each foraging strategy. We can compare those solutions to the squirrel's actual diet to see which strategy the squirrel favors.
    </p>
    <sidebyside>
    <image source="images/fig-minimize-time-eating">
      <description>
        feasible set with different times
      </description>
    </image>
    <image source="images/fig-maximize-energy">
      <description>
        feasible set with different energy consumed
      </description>
    </image>
    </sidebyside>
       
</introduction>

<xi:include href="./section-9-1.xml" />  <!--Properties of Lines-->
<xi:include href="./section-9-2.xml" /> <!--Distance and Midpoint Forms-->
<xi:include href="./section-9-3.xml" />  <!--Conic Sections: Ellipses-->
<xi:include href="./section-9-4.xml" />  <!--Conic Sections:Hyperbolas-->
<xi:include href="./section-9-5.xml" />  <!--Nonlinear Systems-->
        

</chapter> 
<!-- </book>  </mathbook> -->